hello YouTube running last time when we
signed off yesterday I was like never
again are we on here it was like right
except tomorrow morning where we do
project raising but because we're
switching over to a new YouTube channel
adds up hopefully next week so welcome
James Jones to project raising he's
gonna tell us at that about what cubes
spawn is even though the links are in
the description and then we are gonna
brainstorm how to get the resources so
that this project can continue going and
meet James suspicions for keeps fun
alright that cube spawn is an idea based
on the premise that if you convert over
to digital templates for distribution of
goods and remove yourself from the
existing paradigm of physically shipping
goods all over the planet manufacturing
in China and selling in Europe or
selling to Europe and then reselling
into Africa you know there's there's
some very crazy things that happen in
the shipping industry as a consequence
of the way we currently do distribution
so the idea with keeps bond is to make
open source automated machines that
enable people to get to have the
resources at their disposal necessary to
manufacture from these digital templates
and then a lot of goods and it's could
being that it's kind of open-ended you
know what goods well it could be hand
tools for gardening all the way up to
medical prosthesis there's essentially
no limitation on what sorts of goods
could be distributed the initial
machines are relatively small so the
size of the goods is constrained by that
but it's the ideas the system is capable
of self extension so you can manufacture
a lot of them upgrades and improvements
and so forth on the machines themselves
to make them more capable or give them
larger capacities to handle larger goods
or whatever so it's a starting point for
a system that essentially replaces a
significant portion of the existing
manufacturing infrastructure brings it
local and then there are two other
components to it and that is that the
early focus will be on generating
designs for power generation or capture
so solar thermal you know all the
different kinds
wave wind water all that stuff biogas
all of those systems then can be made
you put a keep spawn system in place you
round up materials for whatever system
you want to implement you create local
power system and then you can cut
yourself off from the grid and then the
last part of it is recycling
capabilities so that you can take local
materials and convert them into stock
for the production of goods and the idea
is a feedback loop in design so that the
goods migrate towards higher utilization
of the recycled materials and away from
materials which are either unrecyclable
are not available in the local market
and those solutions being that they're
open-source are pooled in a repository
so that if you saw the problem in
Botswana
maybe the applicable in Boston you you
then taken basically crowd source design
knowledge and allow that those solutions
to propagate to wherever they're
applicable so the machinery part is the
pointy end of this idea but there's a
lot of volume behind it because one of
the early focuses has been agricultural
systems the ability to produce food at
high density locally from for whatever
regardless of climate you know so
Jubilee mentioned she had some
difficulty with basil well I think we
could probably a design and grow chamber
where you could produce all the basil
you could stand in Vancouver and not
have to worry about climactic variations
that create difficulty in that so that's
basically what keeps bond is and what
its purpose is and the sort of meta
application is that the current shipping
paradigm is responsible for 30% of air
pollution ships on the sea there are
50,000 ships of those there are 5,000
container ships the biggest 15 container
ships produce more particulate pollution
than all 770 million terrestrial
vehicles because they're essentially
unregulated in international waters
that's starting to change it hasn't
changed yet and or at least not much and
they burn crappy fuel with a lot of
sulfur in it so you lot of bad stuff
pumped in the environment so cubes bond
addresses that problem
by first of all making goods locally
shouldn't have to ship them and then
secondly by recycling also dive ship the
raw materials and the third thing is
every metropolitan area has enormous
quantities of solid waste that they need
to get rid of well they don't need to
get rid of them they need to utilize
them those materials are actually from
consumer goods that were already desired
in that market which means most of the
materials you need to create to
perpetuate the kind of lifestyle that
we've come to expect without doing the
kind of environmental damage that we
currently are those two things are not
mutually incompatible it's possible to
have a fairly materially rich life it's
kind of like the example I like to use
is silverware you know you have a drawer
for a silverware you throw it away when
you're done with the meal
no you wash it use it again if there is
a use of water there is a use of energy
but that silverware is reused and reused
and reused potentially for decades
possibly even in some cases for
centuries we have silverware in our
cabinets that's been in the family for
you know 75 years and occasionally we
break it out and use it so that's the
kind of thing that I I see across all
consumer goods everything should be
reused and on that basis getting through
the hardware part hardware is hard it's
difficult to build functioning hardware
it's there's a lot of technical
requirements and it's somewhat expensive
if you utilize any of the services that
currently exist in the market to to
assist you and you know building better
quality stuff and maybe you can build in
your own shop or building specialized
things that you may not have the
expertise to build so in with that in
mind I have a pretty substantial
sounding budget that goes along with
completing this project I have a 70%
complete prototype at this point I was
bid a three million dollar cost to
develop the prototype that I have and it
would have taken there's a big research
laboratory in San Antonio called
Southwest Research Institute they're
about a five hundred million dollar a
year design and research thing they
actually have a probe orbiting the Sun
right now they're a pretty sophisticated
engineering facility
and so I got them to do a bid on it and
their bid was three million dollars one
man here I've taken five years used the
machine shop in another business that
was unusual eyes so it didn't cost me
anything
recycled aluminum and materials from
that business that they would just have
sold as scrap I've made these machines
out of chunk and I have 70% complete
prototype at this point that I would
value based on the original bid if I
were using their numbers it's worth
about 2.2 million it's only cost me
about 85,000 and hard costs and it's
cost about nine hundred thousand an
opportunity cost since I have not worked
for anybody but myself for the last five
years for no wages I'm a terrible boss I
don't pay well and the idea is that it
would take about three hundred and fifty
thousand dollars to complete that so if
your investor minded 900k so far in plus
eighty five and hard costs were at about
a million dollars we have a 2.2 million
dollar asset another three hundred fifty
thousand dollars we'll add about another
million dollars worth of value to the
prototype the prototype will act as a
springboard to do demonstrations for
industry partnerships create YouTube
videos to promote the project and in
general as it's kind of at the heart of
the next phase of development which will
be to build somewhat larger machines so
that standard materials from the supply
chain can be utilized to it further
extend the system and to provide
manufactured goods to whomever adopts
these projects the machines cost is
expected to be between 50 and 75
thousand dollars in a retail framework
you know so it's the cost of a luxury
automobile but you compare that to the
existing cost of getting that level of
automation into a facility and it's a
roughly a million so you're getting a
million dollar machine for 50k or 75k
whichever end of the spectrum we end up
at the $350,000 financial breakdown is
that it's about 50k for me to live on
for the next year and that is overkill
I don't need $50,000 but I've dug kind
of a hole by having five years of
having an income and it would be nice to
sort of level things back out again
it'll certainly lower the amount of
pressure that's on that are external to
the project so that the focus can
primarily be on completing what is
necessary to get the prototype
functional and the other 300,000
essentially breaks down in one of two
ways you can look at it either way I've
bit out a number of these machine
designs to see what they would cost for
somebody else to make them and it it's
between fifteen and twenty thousand
dollars so you can look at it as
basically twenty fifteen thousand dollar
projects or fifteen twenty thousand
dollar projects for the remaining
machines machine designs and software
development to complete the prototype
and that's what the three hundred fifty
thousand dollar comes from the shortest
possible breakdown of the analysis and
that is what I have to say about that
all right
thanks James and you are clearly very
knowledgeable in both the like finances
of this and the software and hardware
like you are gonna be the expert on all
of those and the numbers but that's why
this will be fun to play with and see
what can we offer you in that in that
area what can we brainstorm not being
the experts on on that and I don't have
anything in my head at the moment
besides like things either tech one
thing I remember is that this can occur
incrementally it doesn't all have to be
in one lump so it's not really that big
of a number you know 20k is or 15k is
vastly more approachable than 350 and 15
or 20 means a crowd source project so I
have two functioning prototypes so if we
decided to crowdsource something those
machines can be put up as something that
actually works so I have lots of
questions I don't know exactly where to
start but I can just jump in or less a
drill or Jimmy wants to ask him first
we'll see if you handle if they over
loud yeah
yes so there's some details that when
I'm looking over the website that I so
this is partially a suggestion and a
question so these are questions that I
think would come to mind that that I
think would be helpful to move up in
your in your visibility on your website
so it doesn't take you became unit
somehow Bentley you were fine and then
you started yeah I've got to all three
of you were married then when you I
think it might get Otto meeting on your
mic well I'm having I'm having a
technical she thought of me I think the
mic is getting unplug higher visibility
for some issues you're saying well so
for some questions that that tend to
come to mind when you're doing this so
like like on the sheet somewhere it says
that the machines are 2 meters and
that's 2 meters watts to standard metric
2000 millimeters to meters they're
actually 600 millimeters for the first
size of machine and then you're muted
again Bentley here my Pesek meters cubed
for each machine I'm sorry community
meters by 2 meters by 2 meters or like
the capacity there are 600 millimeters
they're actually two metric feet they're
essentially the equivalent of two feet
Imperial you're also muted again Bentley
your mic is just you didn't needed a
meet it
you don't have this issue that iment of
height with me yeah there's 600 so yeah
so it would be helpful to say like
outside dimensions and you know squared
as opposed to just saying 2 meters I
mean a person that's used to working on
text sheets like that might know that
answer but right I'm actually curious
where he saw two meters because I that
numbers is wrong and it's also there's a
two feet I'm sorry close to two feet so
on one of your blog posts but I mean I
didn't
right about 600 millimeters so 300
millimeters was a standard it was
established in chip wafers because it's
about a foot and that way people could
just change the scales and they didn't
have to read build a machine when yeah
in person so it's a good mile or the
scale would be would be helpful
early up in the process I don't know if
this is something to build houses or to
build you know Micro Machines and then
you say a flexible manufacturing process
does that include is that additive
subtractive all the above assembly all
of the above with assembly the initial
prototype consists of eight machines
four machines are blind so which means
work goes in something happens and what
comes back out so they have a very
limited work envelope in all three
dimensions and they are a milling
machine a regular metal cutting milling
machine three axes mill a lathe a robot
and a 3d printer and then the other four
machines that are across the aisle from
them as it were I don't know if you've
seen a picture of the machine so not
sure how well is that what's on the
homepage actually if you go to slash
roadmap keep spawn slash roadmap which
is under the technical menu together the
technical menu then it's got a thing
under there phase one two three four and
and the roadmap if you go the roadmap
page the roadmap page actually has all
of that information it's probably
somewhat because you have to go under
the technical menu it's probably not the
first thing people lead to so we should
probably consider making making that
more prominent yeah it also looks like I
have to go further into each of the
phases to see I mean on the roadmap page
I don't see where it says that it has
those four components this website's
done a lot of evolution and none of it's
necessarily the best
you're muted again Bentley I also want
to see if you've talked to investors but
before we get to that question yeah I
mean I would I would think it would need
to be able to answer kind of all these
yeah you know I think it would be good
to spend we just need your camera on
getting the getting the pitch just I
think there's some room for improvement
that we could help you with
so have you pitched this to investors
yet and what's been your response so far
I pitched this - okay I did a
Kickstarter in 2009 gives you some
timeline I started in 2006 I took
there's a local hacker hacker space a
there's a work co-working space here
that's funded by the guys who own
Rackspace so they're all worth two three
hundred million apiece they're all rich
guys I've met all of them and talked to
him talked to him about this idea and so
forth and they have a accelerator sort
of thing that I spent about three years
trying to pitch this idea to and went
through all of their coaching and
basically they lack the imagination to
to follow the idea it does not have a
one-step to a product there is no market
of product marketability in step one
there are numerous things that have to
be done before you can get to that
that's why the completing of the
prototype then it leads to industry
partnerships because you have a
demonstrable system that you can take in
and there are 200 verticals I think I've
done an X analysis on this North
American industry classification system
so I've gone through their 7700 makes
codes and you know there's probably
2,500 relevant businesses in there
there's a bunch of yeah well
okay so yeah that's getting really far
into the details I think I just wanted
to find out yeah what who you know how
many people have you pitch to so far and
what was their response I mean so I
would say and I Kickstarter and stuff
and then we talk to VCS so my understand
is that usually the VP time turnaround
is like they need a a 10x of their
capital within five to ten years so that
doesn't fit and that's typical I work a
lot different right that's their
hardware has a higher initial investment
I don't and well so you're you're in two
different things one is it's it's
hardware so it has a higher upfront
investment than just digital and then
you're also creating a new more market I
mean this is this is a new idea it does
not exist right so you can buy a lots of
integrated stuff in industry but the
costs are are not something that small
business can approach 90% of businesses
well yeah I mean like I worked for
genetic testing company and they were
automating the the blood the process of
the blood and the testing and putting it
into the gene testing machines and so
there was nothing they could buy
off-the-shelf that did half of that so
it was still half the cost is paying
people to figure out how to fit these
components together
now that's medical which is a little bit
percent yeah maybe it's more of that I
didn't actually look at those numbers so
even in that space having a fully
integrated unit is a pretty new idea I
mean people can probably visualize a
little bit better because they're
billing these things in some companies
the larger companies are building them
in-house but yeah so I
I mean I would say that this is not that
unless you
happened to find it son like 99% of the
venture capitalists that would look at
this it would not be within the
wheelhouse it just in my opinion just
because it is first of all just being a
physical product and then and then
having something to where the market
doesn't exist yet
so it has it have to be something with a
lot of vision and deep pockets and
loneliness to wait I'm looking at right
now pitching to impact capital groups
because they're much more interested in
broad reaching ideas commercialization
is kind of a interest but not their
primary focus so on the 20th I'll be
pitching to a impact Capital Group and
so that mean the variety of pitches
everything from its the Star Trek
replicator you know up to the this is
modular that believe it or not modular
systems like this were patented first in
about 1963 so they're actually older
than I am but the thing is the focus has
always been on automotive manufacturers
scale automation gigantic
hundred-million-dollar systems never has
it been small systems that are benchtop
scale for ordinary manufacturers
ordinary hackerspaces or whatever so the
the focus is different but the
technology is really sort of something
that's already been done well yeah but
yeah it's it's a pretty steep thing now
when you say the 350,000 that's that
gonna get you to walk because that won't
get you to profitability no that just
completes that gets us to the point at
which we can actually demonstrate you
know make a bunch of YouTube videos and
then start to talk to manufacturers
about how would this apply to their
problem and targeting those
manufacturers so that the fit is
appropriate you know is critical because
the first machines have a relatively
limited scope of capability
so so what what do you think do you have
an estimate yet for what it would cost
and I know that this would be way hard
to calculate but in order to get to
where you're I mean if you're looking
are you I guess the question is if I did
it so sustainable how much well no how
much yeah how much to make it a
sustainable product let's not say
profitable but just sustainable yeah how
much investment do you have an idea of
how much invest in it take to get
sustainable it'll take five to eight
million dollars to manufacture enough
units to get them and productize them
better obviously these first cut
machines are not not something I would
sell I would sell a kit for them so that
other people can explore it and do
additional development but it's not
something that's gonna be retail and
coming to create you're gonna you know
bolt it together and run it you're gonna
have to make it so at the current state
when you complete the prototype plans
digital plans get released so that other
people can build them but there is no
product and the I what I'm using as a
model are you familiar with how the
RepRap 3d printer evolved in the market
not specifically but I've heard how they
tell it stuff like they oh okay well
that was in 2006 the plans were released
within a year there were 2,500 machines
in the field there was no central
manufacturing and there was no
distribution network it was just a
hobbyist enthusiasm that built machines
and then began to build more difficult
to make components for each other right
so I mean it sounds to me for most
people looking at this they would
perceive that that any money they donate
to that 300,000 would be a donation I
don't it's not it's not a
an investment I guess I mean it's
investment in society it's not an
investment for property
I mean curve for profit it's definitely
an investment in society
are you saying you did a Kickstarter for
it yeah I did it when it was when
Kickstarter was primarily uh comic books
and poetry
well they do much more manufacturing
stuff now right it's evolved
manufacturing that's why I think it
would be appropriate possibly to pursue
production of these machines as well
yeah I mean another option is just to
say hey you know we'll make the
prototype if you're a Kickstarter then
you will be the first to receive the
videos and the technical plans before
they're released to the public
limitations another option Kickstarter
requires that you have a functioning
prototype if you're gonna peddle a
prototype I have to function well yeah I
mean there's other crowdfunding sites
but kickstart would probably be the best
thing but if you're if your product is
designs having yeah I guess maybe they
just wouldn't even allow it it would
allow the first two machines because
there are demonstrably functional
prototypes to do what they're supposed
to but for the remainder basically what
you would have to do is rob Peter to pay
Paul to you know do development on
additional stuff and that I don't know
what conflicts of interest or difficult
you know whether that would put you in a
bind whether that would put you at risk
to use funds that were supposedly for
the production of one unit to develop
another I don't think that's what
they're after
well I don't yeah I don't know it seems
kind of yeah I'd have to think through
if there's a way around that because if
your product is making a a digital file
with plans you you know can't duke it
would they still say you need a working
prototype well it's the digital file we
haven't made it yet so we can't have a
working you know there might be there's
probably
yeah or and leave in a way that's kind
of realistic it's just maybe we're not
selling the actual physical product so
maybe it would have slightly different
rules but that would take some
investigation but yeah I'm trying to
think of if someone's giving you money
what's some value that we can give them
other than just the seeing a better
future for Humanity themselves in
essence the goal for the machines is
that these produce wealth without money
if you're recycling materials and
turning them into goods but of course
the amount of infrastructure that's
required to arrive at that point is
substantial so it is not that's that's
really where the challenge lies in that
sure if I had these machines running
right now what could I make with them Oh
quite a range of things but I'd have to
buy the materials so because it cost
effective as compared to existing
techniques it's hard to say probably
it's probably on par at best and then if
you do develop all of the recycling
stuff that's another substantial
investment in in development to get to a
point where you can take materials like
PET bottles and you know turn them into
the stock that is useful for producing
some actually applicable product so
there's there's so much lead on this
because I'm building a new industry as
it were there's so much work to do
between the point we're at and the point
at which profitability happens the other
thing is if you only were these machines
what do you care about profitability if
you're applying it to building your
greenhouse and maintaining the
infrastructure of your self-sufficient
village so relevant yeah it's it's what
you're looking for is a bootstrap you
need to figure out some way to iterate
on this in a way that's not draining the
bank or not yeah the closer you can get
to that the better and then Adriel I can
see you wanna so yes two things one for
the the raw materials have you reached
out to any of those projects that are
trying to clean the plastic out of the
ocean
I've looked I've talked to precious
plastics the guy precious plastics I've
reached out to him several times I've
never gotten a response he
too busy or not interested some of the
other smaller plastics may people are
making machines because those this is
open-source the whole idea is that it's
open source which means this is kind of
the borg of open source right will
absorb every other open source project
that has relevance right so working with
those folks I'm open to it I haven't
invested a great deal of effort because
I don't think I'm ready yet I'm not
really to the point where I can say hey
I've got a little bit of money and I'm
really interested in your thing and
let's incorporate it and you know would
you be interested in participating in
that I haven't I haven't got to that
point to where that would be a
reasonable proposition for anybody at
this stage in your reviewing the the Nix
codes and sort of those industries and
what's involved did anything jump out to
you is like oh I could make that you
know with the minimal improvements to
the current set up yes do you see
anything in those industries that may be
like oh for only $20,000 I could get to
a point where now I can make something
that I can sell to those industries yeah
nothing has been quite that close but
there are a couple of things that jump
out vertical applications that are
appropriate and one of them is MRO
maintenance repair and operations so
basically think of it as it's Granger
and a box Granger is a you know a big
supplier of repair parts so the idea
would be you make all special Hardware
on this system instead of buying it for
whatever exorbitant cost the one
manufacturer that's in East was way
ahead is selling it for so MRO is an
application trim out second op for
products you'd make a product now you've
got to be something else to it that's
usually done manually so second op
there's James have you talked to arnesto
in the game bSpace yes Cuba 2.0 and he
he just sent me on Facebook a video of a
prototype I think he's designed in in
software to reclaim
plastic from the ocean itself I just
suggest you guys get in contact I think
you guys can keep out on this hardware
even if it's not a solution to your
funding which i think is kind of to me
the like it sounds to me like what your
customer is is people like you who want
to geek out in this space right you guys
want to like get your hands on and get
this this stuff better for the for the
better world it's how to not market it
to them because they already I mean they
themselves gonna have the same problem
you do they don't have the money they
can't fund it they can't it's to create
a community create that in a way that
it's marketable to an audience that they
want to watch that process happen and
fund it right there's like a million
people who want to put in ten dollars a
year right to be like but that means a
media department that means having
someone who can make the story because
the two people that come to mind one of
whom I really like the concept I think
we have this during our conversation I
don't member from what we talked about
the Global Village set the global
village Construction Set yeah
Marcin Jakubowski I talked to him
extensively in 2008 or so and our first
of all there's a there's a bit of a
personality clash there but secondly his
focus is on was on building all of this
machinery but not really necessarily the
means of production his prop his
projects evolved towards now building
the means to produce those machines
which is where I started so there might
be a better synergy now than there was
then but at that point in time I thought
we had identical goals with very
different tasks to them but it's like
how to not necessarily with them but how
to do what they're doing what you're
doing in a marketable way in game a so
that people want to watch it cuz we want
to have hope for a better world but the
hope for this product is a decade away
right for us to be able to have it on
our block and and print our stuff
so it's making the story of that
enticing as you go the other person that
came to add you-know-who Simone Gert
says I do and I've reached out to her to
shitty robots is her thing and I reached
out to her too and I got no response so
everybody need to keep reaching out to
her or like again like just even
mimicking I mean she's has a personality
that is very designed for this right and
she knows how to do the social media
part you know you know like followers
and now has vacuum by I think like Tesla
or like she has she has money to do her
thing but she's made what she does
marketable and I don't know is that an
area you would want to pursue if there
are people in game B space who were more
into marketing and to tell this story
that means you being on camera it means
you don't I mean like is that right I've
never desired to be on camera the media
channel thing has not really been my cup
of tea
however I'm more than willing to do that
because it does not unlike other efforts
it doesn't take me away from the work so
I can still make progress on the work I
mean how hard is this right I'm on
camera right now so it's not as if this
were any major barrier and I've had
numerous people encouraged me to do you
know you should do a YouTube channel
well I have a YouTube channel but it's
not useful and as of late in the last
since I did the TED talk I was sort of
my first foray into a public speaking
regarding this project so I did the TED
talk and it wasn't in my opinion great
but at least it it pushed the
conversation forward a little bit
because it it mentions all of these you
know things and how we have all these
issues in the world and this this is
that the Nexus manufacturing is half of
the world's economy there are close to
it between shipping and manufacturing it
is half the world's economy it's almost
40 trillion dollars we have an 86
trillion dollar economy so manufacturing
is at the core of solving every problem
we have in society if you solve
manufacturing and make it not pull
and not destroy the environment and so
forth you've solved by extension you
have solved a significant portion of the
problems that are putting us in the
situation where we're facing climate
change with the strong manufacturing
infrastructure that was local you could
put out a carbon capture application and
execute it and probably shorten recovery
to 20 years because it's we don't have
any energy problems we have more than
enough energy to do everything we want
it's just the way we produce the energy
that creates you know the problems and
energy is really a fairly small segment
of the overall world economy manufacture
space that was sorry not the one that I
just want to put that one up first shows
the ships normally vote he's giving
other ideas other routes yeah I think
are do it I think I remember that he
mentioned this before I saw a post
relating to building halls for SpaceX
which is a fairly daunting technical
task but all of the fabrication
equipment for it could be made as a
second or third order production of that
from the system I have in mind so it's
far from impossible
those expert import relations that are
hurting me sorry I'm freaking out loud
could XCOM it that's not helpful
I mean having I think there is something
about having man you but it's not a
prototype that works yet right so like
having it in Cuba having it in places
that are went through a natural disaster
and now hey you have at least a way to
get to get goods net but like there are
tons of those branches right like the
space exploration the cleaning up the
oceans creating a manufacturing for
local in you know more local in Cuba and
which is not like you're not gonna make
it there and then ship it to the United
States and Canada that's not this vision
it is making it in your neighborhood the
other thing is I have no desire
to be hardware manufacturers that's a
very expensive enterprise and it would
be constraining if I built all the
machines that means that they're only
reflecting my vision of how they should
be built and I think the better thing to
do would be to get the first hundred
systems financed and get them out in the
field those systems then build each
subsequent system and the digital design
architecture that creates whatever the
hardware does you know and I've used the
example you know you could build a
turnip sorting machine just stupid
application right but you could build a
turnip sorting machine and then the
vision system that recognizes blemishes
on turnips would be perfectly applicable
to sorting tennis balls or if that
wasn't your thing you could do a few
more modifications and also in that's an
egg grading system it's incremental
because that each solution that you
build can be attitude to do ten other
things and that means that and the
equipment evolves too you start off with
these eight machines well these eight
machines have a real constraint in terms
of what they're up or what they're
capable of doing but a little innovation
a little flexibility somebody comes
along and says hey we could we could
turn this into a you know a 3d meat
printer so we can do that cycle meat in
our community you know that's that's the
kind of thing where their app actually
is no limitation you can reflect
anything that can be done in industry
today can be done in the system the only
thing is is that you have an affordable
entry point to get these machines in
your community so that your supply chain
is short you get rid of shipping they're
automated so you get rid of labor the
cost of goods go down because you remove
those two major expense components you
know that there's a feedback loop that
if you implement it the more you
implement it the better it becomes and
you have a large community of people to
innovate and contribute to it so my
statement has always been if I can
recognize these five years after they
run loose in the field that's probably
been a failure because what will happen
is they will evolve beyond anything I
could have ever thought up and I want to
turn loose of them I want them to
propagate so I want to finish the
prototype and get the machine started
and then let the community take them
wherever they need to go so I I think
if we so we have about 20 minutes left
I'd like us to see if we could
synthesize what we've learned about the
funding options right because that's
your main ask as aspiration in this
right so I mean so we have venture
investment which is hard and this
doesn't quite fit into that very well
unless you can find someone who's used
to actually I can't think of anyone
that's that's investing in such a
far-off disorients research grants were
kind of the other branch of approach
because but unfortunately what I'm
building isn't research it's engineering
and so I actually applied for grants at
the open source robotics foundation it
wasn't a very big grant it was like
180,000 or whatever and the feedback
that I got from them is said you should
pursue this further but this does not
fit our program because we are our
focuses research and this is engineering
well I thought that was pretty good
validation actually you know it didn't
grand but it said oh you're building
something that's real but you know we
don't fund that we build we want fantasy
stuff crazy stuff so yeah so so research
grants is one that's not about a venture
capital we said isn't as a high
probability so donations from individual
people is a different is is a kind of
add another option that just want to see
this exists I don't even really see a
crowd funding
what about patreon he's at picture okay
yeah and that would and that would be
the individual kind of donations for
people that want to see it but if you're
gonna do patreon you will need to start
doing consistent YouTube videos or yeah
you know for your progress because the
like you're doing the progress blog
posts but I don't see many people
donating for that right so I'm just
wracking my brain to see if there's any
other there's like five or six
categories but none of them are great
I'm sorry the people in your space that
do this kind of work like the
construction set people are they
generally people who like to work in
small groups of people or all by
themselves
mmm there's a lot of lone wolves but
there isn't there isn't a great deal of
synergy in the hardware space it usually
is extremely small teams to three people
is exceptional so because somebody gets
an idea you know and your ideas pure and
wonderful and it's actually fairly hard
to explain to other people and other
people have different ideas anyway so it
usually and I'm guilty of that as well a
number of people have offered to help
and I've explained well this is kinda
what I think I need help with and they
go up I don't do any of those things so
it's actually kind of difficult to find
a good fit now as the product approaches
being more complete then that becomes
less true because it's a general purpose
thing that you can see does this and
maybe does to this in a way that could
be improved so then there's then there's
an entry point for somebody with
expertise to come in and say yeah I can
change that make it better
so I was thinking we were talking about
crowdfunding and you have the two
prototypes but you wanted to work on the
next prototype
I think the crowdfunding is there's two
expectations one is you would build what
the prototype is but the assumption is
that you would make some profit off of
that right
usually the profit margins are really
skinny on that but and then that profit
would be what you reinvest into the next
prototype and then you put you put it
back to the cycle so yeah so maybe
breaking this day
- here's the robotic arm piece that you
can use for assembly or here's the
Harrises subtractive you know the the
subtractive manufacturing one here's the
additive manufacturing one which is just
a 3d printer right it's yeah start with
individual boxes but they have to
provide value in and of themselves of
course they'll provide much more value
wants to combine so if it's like here's
box one buy this please
and knowing here's kind of vision we're
gonna add these other box so that might
be kind of a way to do it yeah I think
that's a very I think that's a very
probable marketing strategy to the and
I've resisted it to some degree only
because the individual boxes have have
very little synergy in and of themselves
and furthermore because of the prototype
strategy I've used Delta maker 2 for the
3d printer so the ultimatrix 2 is almost
obsolete now because evolution and 3d
printers has been rapid there's now an
ultimate 3 so if I'm selling an Altima
core to knock off two people is there
much value in that it's hard to see it
well I mean even I mean I guess I
wouldn't even I mean for your boxes I
would I mean does it need to be your own
3d printer or does it need to be that
your assembly mechanism needs to be able
to interact with it with existing 3d
printers right one of the there's a good
reason for it but one of the corners I
painted myself into is that everything
is dimensionally consistent and as a
consequence to that the designs that are
available in the market are have to be
modified basically to fit and so that
makes them custom it doesn't make them
entirely custom because almost
everything about that printer is the
same as it is in the ultime Kerr
but there are subtle dimensional
differences and various other things
which means that you can't just buy
parts for the other device and then make
use of them in my device
and there I could go so lengthy Lisbon
so but even aren't they are they too big
in one dimension the the problem no
they're actually my my printer is only
subtly different but in choosing a
standard I ended up with dimensions that
are slightly different from a standard
ultimate or so I can't take that I can't
use all the mecha parts yeah well I I'm
just thinking that that may be something
you'll have to consider I mean I know
you've thought about it but unless
you're going to try and compete with all
the 3d printers building something
that's adaptable I mean as long as the
printers within a 3d set and then you're
you're having to do assembly anyways you
just need to figure out a way to get the
3d printed part into the assembly Bay or
you can have the arm from the assembly
Bay be able to go out of the dimensions
and pick it up I mean you have a process
for moving things between the different
units right yeah because I don't I think
it's gonna be you know it's yeah so
doing the 3d printer I think would be
hard and so if you could find it might
be worth reconsidering that decision and
figuring out how to use existing 3d
printers at least temporarily though I
think the core thing that you're making
that doesn't exist in the world because
they're seeing there's lots of CNC
machines there's lots of three 3d
printers but there's not an assembly
right arm the biggest thing is that you
could build you could duplicate the
function of this with eight standalone
machines and a conveying setup between
them and robotics but then every problem
you solve in that framework is a
integration unique integration problem
that you're going to have to resolve if
you change the machine so that
the value in pre integrating everything
as I said that if you're setting up a
million dollar plant you can expect that
in that million dollar plant two hundred
thousand is hardware eight hundred
thousand is integration getting all yeah
unless yeah I mean one other option you
probably already thought this through
and said it wouldn't work but unless you
automate the integration so instead of a
conveyor belt solution you use the
robotic arm from the assembly function
to be also the thing that moves parts
from piece to piece and that's it could
it would just be a programming and
vision recognition rather than try and
figure out how to make a printer that
will integrate with a conveyor belt
right well and conveyor belt is sort of
misleading it's actually a plate that
travels along it's a conveyor belt that
conveys a base and that base then has a
lot of different modular automation that
attaches to it for different purposes so
you know there's this is that's what we
do is we end up getting off in the weeds
every time I talk about this because
there are so many solutions that are
folded into it that really do not
present or do not offer themselves as
simple explanations well yeah so it's
it's finding but I mean if yeah so one
of the options is to start selling small
parts right small parts we have the
kraut way of the donations with the
small part crowdfunding we have venture
capital and we have grants and funds
right those are really your only four
options now there is one other thing
that I can bring up so about three weeks
give or take the expectation is that
there will be a puzzle game released
that's branded as cube spawn maker I
didn't build it somebody else did
it's a the idea is to evolve that game
environment which is based on Godot
which is the open source game engine the
idea is to evolve that towards being
a simulation environment a VR AR
interface virtual reality augmented
reality interface to these machines and
to build in the creation tool chain
necessary to basically create a model
that can then be manufactured by
machines so in the early stages none of
those things will be true it's just a
game but the individual that's backing
that he thinks that the game may produce
revenue and then that revenue can be
applied to developing the actual
hardware so one of the things in my
project is where I focused on getting
functional Hardware so that I could use
it for demonstration the shift lately
has been towards focusing on the digital
assets and actually distribute this as a
virtual environment that does not
actually produce anything but accurately
simulates all of the functions in the
environment so that people can get their
hands on it by downloading it instead of
having to commit to all this expensive
hardware and all the complexity that's
involved in actually doing things in the
physical world so I didn't really
mention that in the beginning because
it's another giant idea that sort of
attached itself to the side of the
project that if we focus instead
primarily on in a game dimension and
then you've got a you know VR AR is hot
stuff and virtual virtual environments
are becoming very mature and and
especially for things that's clearly
defined as mechanical environments you
know if you're trying to do a jungle
well it looks a little funky but if
you're trying to do a machine looks
pretty good so that's another potential
Avenue is that focusing all focus on the
game make the make the virtual
environment the product initially and
then use the proceeds from that to
develop the physical side of the system
so I don't know if that helps your
perception at all but it's another
Avenue
so yeah of all of these kind of kind of
funding categories do you have a lean
towards well no I don't because it's a
whatever words I've kind of kept every
iron in the fire that I can fit there
might be a fee see that has vision the
impact investors might think this is a
good idea the game development might
provide funding so any of those things
are viable avenues if they work the
amount of effort that I'd I have over
the course the last three months or so I
pretty much stopped developing hardware
I've continued to draw for development
of hardware but there are a whole number
of factors as to why over the last three
months I haven't done a lot of actual
hardware building I haven't cut a lot of
metal and the focus has been shifted to
back to how do we raise money so that if
I can raise the 350k this is about a
four month project to completion it's
four months or so until there's
functioning Hardware all eight machines
because the machines are very simple
mechanically and technically so getting
functioning machines opens the door to
the next step which is to find an
industry partnership so raising the
money has become the highest priority
and doing it through one of these the
four means or so that we've mentioned
VC's in fact developing the game and
getting something out of that or selling
kits or selling a components out of the
system and whether that's by
crowdsourcing or whether it's by some
other means yeah yeah it's just really
tough because I don't think any of those
in any of those situations people are
driving enough value that it would be an
easy sell for them to say yes so we need
to
I would suggest need to find a smaller
the smallest chunk on which you can you
know that you can derive some value to
someone well I mean the more the more
people that you get seeing it and
understanding the that's that increases
your luck surface area so then you'll
probably you could find someone who
wants to invest some money or has some
technical chops maybe find it a few over
the people that they would build the
prototypes and you know on their own
time and that saves you some time or
something like that so yeah I that would
be the only kind of immediate thing as I
think making a weekly YouTube video
showing where you are and what the
machines do would be the quickest thing
and taking Qatar and then just keep
hitting these things that guess the
other option is is I would have a pitch
deck like just one or two slides or a
one-page thing that's that hits each of
these funding options like the VCS will
want to know how far do you have to get
till it's profitable the donation people
would want to know how long until you're
actually benefiting human beings and if
it's selling to Kickstarter or some sort
of crowdfunding they want to know what's
the smallest unit of value you can
provide and how much would that cost and
how long like this
essentially the value proposition for
each different Avenue yeah yeah if you
want to kind of make those I'd be happy
to look over them sometime and just I
just get my feedback I actually probably
have bits and pieces lying around that I
can stitch together
damnit I was gonna say something and
that just slipped away was pretty
relevant the getting a value proposition
together for the different avenues of
funding is probably something that won't
take very long which means that at least
get some feedback and I'm a little dense
you know I don't really learn that fast
but a lot of people have said that the
media push is probably the one thing
that lacks the most if you're trying to
tell people why and how you're doing
something then maybe you should actually
tell them why and how you're doing it
instead of assuming that they can infer
that from the little bit of literature
you've laid out I had someone put it
pretty much those terms like a future
vision video that explains it like it's
already happening right like that Star
Trek mm-hmm this is what this looks like
right and so people can like put
themselves in that in that place and
they're gonna be more likely but then
they also want to see the journey along
the way right they're not really gonna
invest and invest is wrong work they're
not gonna donate for a 10 year out
future they might because honestly this
is awesome but it's 10 years out awesome
right if not 20 30 years out comes to
mind as an example of why not to do that
cuz great vision beautiful architecture
fantastic stuff no way to get there so I
list which one
this project has this great idea you
know let's make circular cities let's do
all this great stuff but then how do you
get there doesn't say you know that
there really is no plan on how do you
start executing that today in a game a
world to get to game B and I think I
built the bridge but I haven't
articulated that well enough clearly
because people don't see it enough and
large enough numbers for them to say hey
here's a hundred bucks why don't you get
that going so I way that it appeals to
meaning in like cartoony here's how we
hit or they mean like a very viral video
like something that does speak to
everyone
this is this is what this could happen
like that cell phone right of the
interchangeable pieces that never went
anywhere that that thing of it and
honoring that it's in the future but
like hey this is the vision we're going
towards I think peep there are tons of
people out there who would put 50 100
bucks or five bucks 10 bucks right
whatever is within their budget towards
that they might not necessarily put 5
bucks a month towards it right because
they need to get value keep coming back
in order to be able to do that but you
might also find those people in doing
that like the people who are like yes I
want to like tell this story along the
way and then you don't need to tell the
story and this is kind of more of the
meta side of things that we're trying to
work on is like all of these things have
the same problem the people the funding
the story the people with the ideas
aren't necessarily the greatest people
at telling our stories to get them out
there right and how do we bring those
people together so that we can do this
and we're all in the beginning stages
but it's coming it's coming
I'm that's just the way it is I'm
actually I know some stuff media
promotion is not one of those things so
that's one of the reasons why things are
as they are and that's probably the case
across all of these projects as somebody
with domain knowledge that's useful for
a particular purpose but they do not
have a team of domain knowledge that is
necessary to to span the the problem and
the problem is that gotta sell it to
somebody I mean even if you're just
selling it as an idea and so that means
somebody who understands sales that's
that's where I feel that with my the
game project that guys all about selling
stuff he's done a great job he's he's
got people to buy tokens that for a game
that doesn't exist you I mean we are
past the hour mark I just want to wrap
it up if there's anything left for you
to say you can say that James I'm going
to mentioned that all right for anyone
watching this video that you can donate
to the patreon it is in the description
for James and go to the cube spawn
website and see what it's all about and
help move this vision
Forbert maybe your maybe you're a
crowdfunding expert and you can come
help create the story or maybe you can
get a feedback in the comments on how to
put the information you want in the
website so that you can go right to the
answer you're looking for
all right about YouTube now forever